This meeting is being recorded.
All right. Okay. So I have about two hours to go through a ton of stuff.
This is not going to be a follow-along thing because I'm going to move pretty fast
with a lot of stuff that I need to cover.
But hopefully the recording will give you insights into everything that I'm doing.
The first thing I'm going to do here is turn on screencast.
Okay. So here on the left side of my screen, you'll see what mouse buttons I'm
clicking as I click them, and also what keys I'm pressing, so that later when you
watch the video, you'll know exactly what commands I'm using to do everything that
I do. Hopefully, that will help. I will tell you right now that Blender requires a
lot of keyboard shortcuts, and these things are not going to be intuitive to you at
all, but you'll learn them, and eventually it will become second nature. All right.
So with that, let me get started. If you don't know who I am, my name is Rico
Contim. I graduated from the Fab Academy program, I think in 2022.
I don't remember anymore. I've been teaching ever since. I live in Kamakura, Japan.
I run my own lab. I just got done with a kids' class, and they left a disaster area
over there that I'll have to clean up after this. But I love working with kids.
They are amazing.
I've taught Blender to kids as young as four and a half years old.
There's one kid here who's a huge fan of dinosaurs, and he's already been modeling
dinosaurs on Blender since he was six years old. So if he can do it, you can do it.
It will require a little bit of work to understand it, but
it's not impossible. Okay.
With that, I'm going to start off by giving you a tour of the user interface for
Blender. Most of the time when you turn on Blender, it should look something-- Am I
sharing screen? I'm not sharing screen.
Let me- No
... go ahead and start doing that.
All right. I think I'm sharing screen now.
Most of the time when you start Blender, you'd see an interface that looks
something like this. And let me walk you through it using my new fancy tool here
where I can annotate. So what I want you to pay attention to is that there are
actually just a few windows. Okay, so
you've got this giant window here. Okay.
I'm going to call this one,
one, and you've got a side window. Let me see. Oh, boy, this is not going to work.
My annotation is not going to work. Okay, so let me get out of this.
You've got this big giant window, and its name is the 3D Viewport.
And this is where all of your modeling will occur.
Every time you manipulate something, this is where it's going to show up.
On the upper right-hand corner is another window here called the Outliner.
And the Outliner is like the-- If you use Windows, it's a Windows Explorer.
If you use a Mac, what is it called on a Mac?
I don't know, File Manager or whatever it is.
It basically lists absolutely everything that is in your current file.
So you probably can't read it, but it says here Camera, Cube, and Light.
So in my scene right now, there are three objects.
I've got the cube, and you notice when I click on it, it highlights it over on the
right-hand side as well. I've got a light here, which is a light bulb, and then
over here I have a camera. Okay? So this lists absolutely everything that you have
in your scene. If I add another object, for instance, if I copy this object here
and I put it over there, now I have two cubes. I have Cube and Cube 1. All right?
So if you need to know, yeah, this will have everything that you need.
All right. And then over on the lower right-hand side is the Properties menu.
And this is the most powerful window within Blender here.
If I click on the cube, you see that there are several icons, maybe 12, a dozen
icons here, and each one of them are property settings for some aspect of Blender.
And there
are too many for you to remember, but the ones I want you to pay attention to are,
there's one here that looks like the back of a DSLR camera, and I'm going to try to
draw it here.
Okay. And it looks like this, a DSLR.
Something like this with, oops, buttons like this. Okay? The back of a DSLR camera.
This is your Render Properties menu. Okay? So please pay attention to that.
And then below that is one that looks like a printer.
Okay. I don't know if any of you have Blender open, but it looks something like
this.
Okay, and this is your Output Properties menu.
We'll be eventually working with that.
And then you skip a few down, you see one that looks like a water droplet.
That one is your scene. So, okay, one more again.
DSLR is your Render menu, the printer is your Output menu, the
water droplet is your Scene menu. The only reason I ever go to the Scene menu is to
set my units, like what do I want to work on?
You'll see here there's a subsection called Units, and here's where I define
whether I want to be working in meters or centimeters or whatever.
The default is meters. And for today, I'm just going to leave it as is.
Skip down a couple more. By far, the magic of Blender is this tool, the one that
looks like a blue wrench. Blue wrench icon is the Modifier icon, and we'll be
going back to this one. So this is a way to take geometry in Blender and give it
extra special features at the push of a button.
So, for instance, I'm going to go to Add Modifier, Generate Subdivision
Surface, and my cube is going to change into this.
So I took each one of the six faces of the cube, and I subdivided it into four
faces per the original six faces. So I now have 12 faces on this cube.
And what you need to know about modifiers is that it's non-destructive, meaning
it's a preview of what it would look like if I applied this modifier.
But if I decide to delete this modifier with this X mark here, the
manipulations, the modification to the geometry disappears.
So it's a way to preview what it will do to your object until you actually lock it
in. Skip a bunch more, all the way to the bottom, you see a red checker ball.
Red checker ball is where you apply the materials.
Right now, this cube has
got the default white color. So here, if you want to change the color to red, if
you want to make it metallic
or something like that, that's where you would do it.
So this is the materials aspect. Okay?
I'll cover all of that in greater detail later on.
Okay.
Screencast letters are a little bit too big.
Let me change that down a bit.
Would you like to start the recording? I thought I did. Did I not?
I don't know. I am
not...
Yeah. I thought I did. Okay. I can see it.
All right.
And then lastly, the one at the bottom here, I'm going to call this the auxiliary
window
because you can change it to anything.
Currently, it is the timeline functionality, which means it's used for animation.
And just to let you know, every single one of these four windows can be changed to
anything you want. On the upper left-hand corner is a little
icon. If you click on that, it'll give you options of absolutely everything that
you could turn that window into. For example, if I want a second 3D viewport, I can
go there and select 3D Viewport, and now I have a second window that will show me
what model I'm working with, okay?
For the time being, I'm going to leave it on timeline, and I'm going to make it
smaller so that I can see
my big window here. Any questions so far?
So four big main windows: 3D Viewport, Outliner, Properties,
and Auxiliary. And in the Properties menu, you want to focus on the back of
DSLR, which is Render, the printer, which is Output,
the water droplet, which is Units, the blue wrench icon, which is Modifier, and
the red checker ball, which is Materials. All right?
It's like driving a car. There are lots and lots of things you can do in your car,
but the first thing you need to learn is steering wheel, gas and brake, and turn
signal. Beyond that, everything else you can figure out later. Okay? Okay.
So with that, let's go back to the 3D properties window, the viewport window here.
A couple of other things you need to see.
Upper right-hand corner, you see four balls of different
designs. The farthest one on the left will turn is the
wireframe view. These are the view modes for your
geometry. And it goes from wireframe to solid view, to
render preview, to full render. And for the most part, when you're
modeling your objects, you want to stay in either wireframe mode or solid view.
These are the least computationally demanding on your computer.
As you move to render preview or the fully rendered thing, it's going to demand
more from your PC, from your GPU, and if you happen to have a weak computer, this
is what's going to crash your computer.
So stay on the wireframe or the solid view to do your modeling.
Another thing I want you to pay attention to is over here on the left, you see a
window called Object Mode. This is the
primary
geometry manipulation mode is Object Mode.
And in Object Mode, you're going to be working with the, I'm going to say, the
macro transformations of your geometry, meaning the big things.
You're going to make it bigger or smaller, you're going to move it around, or
you're going to rotate it. You're not going to be adjusting fine features.
So the big picture manipulations of your mode.
Also, we're in Object Mode now, and we're going to change that later, but I just
want you to be aware where the mode adjustments are.
Other than that,
we're going to start doing some navigation in this window.
So this is where I ask you to have a three-button mouse, because you can do this
with a track pad. I don't quite know.
I think it's like one finger, two fingers, all these other manipulations, which I
don't quite know, but if you Google it, you can probably do it.
Personally, because I want things to be able to be finely controlled, I use a
three-button mouse.
With a three-button mouse, some things you need to be able to do.
So if you press the middle mouse button and move your mouse left and right, you can
use this to orbit around your object.
So as you do anything in a 3D software, the ability to orbit and make sure that
things are happening in the front of your object, the back of your object, the side
of your object, the way you want it to be, is critical.
So middle mouse button rotate is orbit.
If you roll the middle mouse button, I think that should be intuitive to you, is
zooming in and out. If you hold the control key on your keyboard, or command on a
Mac, and then press the middle mouse button. Oops, sorry, not command, shift.
The shift button, and then middle mouse button, and you drag it, you can pan around
your working space. Okay, so if you need to move it that way.
So once again, middle mouse button by itself, orbit.
Middle mouse roll in and out is zoom.
And then shift and middle mouse button will allow you to pan around your screen.
And if that's too much for you to remember, there are actual icons here you can use
to do the same thing. So the one that looks like a magnifying glass, if you left
mouse click on that, and then you drag it up and down, you can zoom.
The hand is pan. So if you left mouse click on that and you move your mouse around,
you'll pan. Orbit will require the use of this, the gumball.
So if you click in the gray area of the gumball with your left mouse button and
then move it around, you can rotate, look up, down on your object, because that's
the same thing as orbiting. Okay. So now on the subject of the gumball, you'll
notice that it comes in multiple friendly colors like red, green, and blue.
Those things correspond to the axes that you see here on Blender in
the viewport. So we're missing blue, so I can go ahead and go to overlay and click
Z here to show the blue line as well. All right.
So what I want you to do or think about from now on, whenever you work on Blender,
is that
minus Y, the green axis should be always going from the lower left-hand corner to
the upper right-hand corner. That's the Y-axis.
The X-axis should always go from the upper left-hand corner down to the lower
right-hand side, and then Z-axis, top to bottom, okay?
If you orient in this way, then you know that when I look at my cube here, this is
the front face of my object. This is the left side, of course, the right side on
the opposite side, the back, top, and bottom.
So whenever you get confused about what you're looking at, reorient to this
orientation with minus Y in this location, and you know that you're looking at the
front face of your object, okay? And I'll tell you why that matters later.
So if you want to look at the front face of your object, you'll click on minus Y,
and it will snap to the front of your object.
If you want, alternatively, if you want to look at the top of your object, you can
click on positive Z, and it will snap to the top.
It's hard to understand right now because we're looking at a cube and all the faces
look the same, but just generally, that's how you would snap to different
viewpoints of your object. All right.
I really don't want to see my camera, which is this black triangle right now.
So I can go over to my outliner and click on the eyeball icon next to camera, and
that's going to hide my camera, and I'm going to click to do the same thing to
light. That way, then it's not involved in my modeling at all.
Any questions so far? Are we good with navigation?
You can help me out by doing the thumbs up key,
or just give me a thumbs up to let me know that I'm speaking in a way that you can
actually understand. All right. With that, let's start playing with this cube.
So we're going from user interface to manipulation to view mode,
object mode, to now working on the cube itself.
So to manipulate any object, first you need to click on it to select it.
Once you've selected the object, you'll see a yellow outline indicating that you
have selected the object. All right, so the first keyboard shortcut command is
G.
G allows you to move the object.
Now, you're asking me why is it not M for move? Why is it G for move?
It's because M is a keyboard shortcut used for something else in Blender, and so
they use G for grab. So you're grabbing and moving the object.
That's what G stands for, okay? And so once you grab it, you can move it wherever
you want in 3D space.
If you're in the middle of a command and you want to cancel it, you hit the escape
key, and that brings it back to where it was before you moved it around.
And if you move it, G, and I left mouse click and leave it at a
new position, and you want to go back, Control Z or Command Z will bring you back
to, will undo the command. Okay? This is the same as many other software out there.
All right? Now, what's cool about it is, and the reason why I spent so much time on
X, Y, and Z earlier is you can constrain the motion of the cube or the
object by adding an axis modifier after you type the G key.
So if I want only to move in the X-axis, you would type G followed by X, and now
I'm constrained to moving only on the X-axis. Okay? Escape to get out of that.
If I want to move on the Y-axis, it's G and Y, and then I move only in the Y.
If I want to move only in the Z-axis, it's G and Z, and then moving up and down
only. Okay? So it's good to have that constraint.
All right, so that's moving. The next transformation command is scale.
Okay? Let's make the cube bigger or smaller.
Luckily, the shortcut key is easier to remember. It's S for scale.
So if I type S, a line will-- Let me make a suggestion when you use the
scale. Don't have your cursor directly on your object.
Have it be slightly outside your object.
Hit the S key, and as you drag your mouse away from the object, it'll get bigger.
If you move it towards the center of the object, it'll get smaller. Okay? So S key.
And Escape to get out of that. And just like G, you can add axis modifiers to
your command to constrain its scale. So I want to make this thing taller.
I would do S and Z and constrain it to the Z-axis, so when I scale it, it only
scales in one direction. Similarly, if I want to make it wider, S and X, I can do
constrain it to the X-axis, S and Y to make it longer or shorter from front to
back. Okay.
Last but not least, the third of the transformation keys is rotation.
Shortcut key R. Okay? And similar to the other ones, if you modify that with
a axis, like for instance, when modified to the Z-axis, it will rotate with the
blue line as its center of rotation.
Similarly, R,
X will use the red line as its center of rotation, and
R, Y will use the green line as the center of rotation.
If you do not use any of the modifier keys and you do rotation, the axis
that it will use for the rotation will be the imaginary axis between your face and
the screen. So if I do R right now and rotate it, it uses this imaginary line
between face and screen as the center of rotation.
Okay. Good so far?
Good. All right. Thank you, Tina, for the thumbs up.
Makes me feel infinitely better that I know what I'm doing.
All right, so after this, let's go on and manipulate the fine aspects of this cube.
It's a really boring cube right now. Let's do something fun.
I mentioned that we are currently in object mode.
In order to get to micro adjustments, we need to go into edit mode.
The shortcut key to get between object to toggle, between object mode and edit mode
is the Tab key on your keyboard. So if you hit Tab, you'll see that the top left
window here changes from
object to edit, and you notice that your cube has extra features now.
It has these little dots, okay, on the corners, for instance.
And so if I select outside to deselect anything, and I select this particular
corner, and then now I can apply any of my transformation keys, right?
If I hit G for move or grab, now I can just move that corner, and I can start
playing around with its shape. Okay.
I can take this corner, and I can constrain it to axis just like before.
For instance, G and then Z, I can move this corner up, and I can take this one and
can say G and X, I can move it in the X direction.
And now I have a much more interesting object than a cube.
Similarly, you can scale things. Oh, I forgot to mention, there are three selection
modes that are possible in edit mode.
Currently, we're in the vertex select mode, which means you can select one of the
dots at the corner. The middle one here, first of all, the vertex select mode, the
shortcut key for that is the number one on your keyboard.
The second selection mode is edge select mode, and that's two on your keyboard.
If you're in edge select mode, instead of selecting corners, you'll be selecting
one of the many edges that defines your
object. And just like before, you can use any of the transformation commands, move,
scale, rotate on your selection. So I'm going to G and I can move it.
I can S to scale it. I can R to rotate it, the selected
edge. Okay. And now, like I said, I have a much more interesting object now.
Last but not least, if you put three on your keyboard, you get to the face select
mode, and you'll select one of the faces of the object that you have.
And again, you can manipulate it. So G, I can move it out here,
R to rotate it, whatever you want to do.
Okay?
So far, so good? So edit mode, micro adjustments, all of the transformation
commands that you used earlier, including the axis constraints, will work on the
object. I'm going to return it to
the cube form here by doing undo
many, many times. And one thing, you notice that I've done 26 undos to get
my manipulations back to the cube.
The first thing I would do whenever you get into Blender is to increase the number
of undos that you're capable of using.
So you do that by going to Edit, Preferences,
System. And here under Memory Limits, there's
a category called Undo Steps. The default is something like 16 steps or 32 steps.
I made mine 150 because I make mistakes all the time, and I want to be able to
redo, undo, undo, undo, and get to a point where I'm happy with.
That's one way to sort of,
to control the history, the modification history to your object.
Another very useful way, and I haven't done this yet, to save my object or
my file, you shouldn't be surprised, it's Control + S or Command + S, and this
saves it, and you can save it wherever you want.
I'm going to save it here under the name Tutorial.
Okay. Like that. Save.
And now I'm going to make a bunch of manipulations to my object here.
Well, actually, you know what? No, it's okay.
And then, I don't know, move this like this, take this face,
rotate it, take this corner
and move it up. Okay, so that's my new object.
Now, I'm not 100% sure I like this object, and maybe I want to go back to the cube.
So one way to save different versions of the same file is under File,
there's Save, Save As, Save Copy, and the last one here, Save Incremental.
So if I choose Save Incremental, I told you that my file name is currently
Tutorial, but if I do save incremental, my name of my file is now Tutorial
1. So now I have two files that have the same shape.
I have Tutorial and Tutorial 1. And if for whatever reason I don't like what I've
just done here, I can revert back by going to File, Open Recent, Tutorial,
and I can go back to my cube shape. Okay?
So if you're doing an incredibly complex model, and you're not 1,000% sure that
what you do next is going to destroy all of the wonderful work you've created so
far, you can do save incremental to save different
milestone points within your file so you don't mess up some wonderful work that
you've done before, and you have a point to return to.
Did you catch that? Is that okay? Thumbs up, Tina? All right. Wonderful.
Thank you very much.
All right, so, a new command for you now that we're in edit mode.
I mentioned that you can take these vertices and manipulate it.
What if you want more vertices to play with? Let's change the shape of this thing.
I'm going to quickly make a perfume bottle out of this lovely cube, okay?
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to hit A for all,
and I'm going to scale it in the Y direction to squash it.
Then I'm going to make a Chanel bottle, for instance, right?
So scale in the Y direction. I'm going to squeeze it in a little bit to give it
more of a-- Actually, I don't know what a Chanel bottle looks like.
This is going to be my version of a Chanel bottle.
But, all right, so we're going to need some kind of
neck for my bottle and then
a top cap for my bottle. So instead of adding a bunch of geometry, I'm just going
to take my existing geometry and manipulate it.
Hitting three to go into face select mode, I'm going to select the top surface.
I use the I command to do an inset,
okay, to create a new kind of sub-face.
I'm going to scale this sub-face to make it more square by scaling it in the X
direction to make it more square.
All right? I'm going to hit the E key to extrude the shape up.
Okay, so that's my neck of my perfume bottle. Now I'm going to make the cap.
So what I can do is I'm going to extrude it one more time.
But first I want to go bigger, so I'm going to do E and followed by S.
So extrude and scale at the same time to do the opposite of inset and go on the
outside like this. Okay. And then from this flat plane, I'm going to go up,
E to go up, this is going to be my perfume bottle hat.
And to make it more interesting, I'm going to scale the top a little bit to give it
a little bit of shape.
And then extrude it again, scale it again,
and extrude it one more time. All right, so this is my lovely perfume bottle made
out of just inset extrusion and a little bit of scaling. Okay.
I'm going to hit Tab to go back into object mode and hit G, Z to move this up above
the work plane.
All right, now we're going to
give it some materials. With this object selected, I'm going to go to the red
checker ball on the properties window here, click New to create a new material.
So the bottom of the perfume bottle should be clear glass.
So what I'm going to do is, first I'm going to call this thing clear
glass. Actually, I'm going to make it blue so that there's a little bit of color.
Blue glass.
And currently, the surface type here is called Principled BSDF.
I don't want that. I want it to be
glass. So I'm going to click this Principled BSDF, and instead choose Glass BSDF.
I'm going to click on Color and change it to be slightly blue.
And if you want to see what that looks like, you can go to Preview and you can see
this is what it would look like. I'm going to take the roughness value and make it
to zero so that it becomes very, very shiny and clear.
And now if I go to Render Preview, the third view mode here, you can see that my
object,
it's not see-through yet because I'm not in full render mode.
If I go to full render mode,
okay, and I turn on my light.
Where's my light? Over here. Control G, X. Let's move it here.
Need to make my light a little bit stronger, I guess. Why is it not showing up?
Huh.
All right, I don't like this light.
I'm going to delete this light by hitting the delete key on my keyboard.
I'm going to Shift A to add. So Shift A.
When you're in the object mode modeling window, Shift A allows you to add anything.
It allows you to add a new geometry. It allows you to add a new light.
So here I'm going to add an area light. I like area lights.
G, Z to move the area light up, S to scale it so it's a little bit bigger.
Then I'm going to go to--
When I select the light, the properties menu changes a little bit and I have at the
very bottom a light bulb icon in green, and right now the power of that light is
10. I'm going to make that 1,000 and see if I get more light on my object.
Why is it not showing me clear? Maybe I need to add one more thing.
I'm going to add a plane at the bottom of this scene. Mesh, plane.
Scale it up
so that it has something to look at.
I'm going to click on the red checkerboard icon and make the plane black color
or gray so that-- Oh, wait a minute.
I'm not quite sure why I'm not-- Well, no, it is transparent.
You can kind of see that the yellow line is crossing through the back of this.
I think I have to render this in order to get it to be clear.
Anyway, you'll have to take my word for it that currently this bottle has a glass
feature. Now you're saying to me, "I don't want the top of this thing to be glass.
I want it to be, say, black plastic or something like that.
How can I localize material assignment?" You do that by entering into edit mode.
So Tab to get into edit mode. I'm going to hit three to do face select, and I'm
going to select the-- First of all, I need to add a new material.
So I'm going to go over here, click on the plus, make sure you're in the red
checkerboard icon. Click plus to add a second material.
Click New, and let's make the top bright red. I don't know.
I know Coco Chanel would be screaming at me for using such horrific colors, but
I'll say red plastic
as the name. And you can play with the roughness to make it less or more shiny, up
to you. I'm going to make it very shiny by reducing the roughness.
And now, to apply that to the top part here, I'm going to click on the face that
I want. If you hold down the shift key, you can continue to select other faces.
Okay, I'm going to rotate this around, make sure I get everything rotated around.
All right, so this is the part I want to be red plastic.
Make sure you select red plastic, and underneath there's a button called Assign.
When I click Assign, the top of this object is now going to be a different
material. So that's how you do localized material assignment. Okay?
All right, so now you have a not so beautiful object, and want to see what it looks
like if you render it, okay? Here's where we go back to the properties menu, the
very top icon, the second to top icon, which looks like the back of the DSLR.
Okay, right now we are in EV mode. That's probably why the, what do you call it?
The transparency is not showing up very well.
By the way, EV was what was used in the movie Flow to do the entirety of its
animation rendering. I have a reasonably good computer with a graphics card, so I'm
going to go and use Cycles, which is a more advanced, more realistic rendering
mode. And in fact, I'm going to make sure that my GPU is involved in the rendering
process. And I'm going to just do a sample render here for you.
So max samples, I'm just going to reduce this to 32 for now to make this go a
little bit faster. And to render out this image,
you need to set the camera to look at this image.
This is going to go fast, my apologies.
So View,
Align View, Align Active Camera to View, like so.
And then I need to hit the N key to pop out the side here, go to View,
and hit Lock to 3D Cursor and Camera to View.
And then I can zoom in and out to position my object nicely into my view port as I
want it. Okay, we'll leave it like that. N key to hide the side panel.
And then you go to Render, Render Image,
and it will render out your image.
Okay, and you can see now that it's glass and plastic, okay, as we tried to make
it. Of course, you could spend a lot more time on lighting and material adjustments
to get this to be more beautiful, but this is the beginning of it.
Once you have a rendering that you like, if you want to actually download it for
use in your documentation or whatever, you can go to Image, Save, and then
obviously choose a place. I'm going to save it into downloads, and I'll call it
tutorial render.
Okay, so now if I go to my Windows Explorer,
go to Downloads, I have a file here called tutorial render that I can-- Are you
looking at it? I'm hoping you see it. You seeing my Windows Explorer? Yes, you are.
Okay, so I double-click on tutorial image.
You'll see that
I have this image that I rendered out.
All right, so that was a ridiculously fast tour through the fundamentals of
Blender.
How many of you are panicking that you regret your decision to join this session
today?
All right, so far so good?
Okay.
All right, I'm going to hide my lovely plane and perfume
bottle, and I'm going to model up something else.
I'm going to model up a very simple cartoon character and to show you some other
techniques that you will need if you want to model up
clothing or whatever. Okay. One of the key aspects of this week is mesh
manipulation, and Blender is a mesh manipulation software.
So let me give you an example. The plane that we used to be the background or the
floor of our scene
is just
as it is indicated. It's just a flat
square plane. If I hit
Tab to go into edit mode, I see that it has four corners.
So this is a mesh with zero subdivisions, okay?
Now I'm going to turn it into a real mesh by right mouse clicking and hitting
Subdivide. So now instead of being one
plane with one shape inside, it's got four planes.
I'm going to do that again, subdivide one more time, one more time, one more time.
So this is a mesh. It is a surface with lots of control points on top of it.
So if I go back, hit one to go into vertex mode, this surface now has lots and lots
of points that I can manipulate. So imagine this is a handkerchief and I want to
make it look all flowy and stuff like that.
I can go in here and select a couple of these points, shift key and select a few of
these vertices and do GZ to move it up. Okay?
But that's not very satisfying because only those points are moving up.
So what you can do is there's a button up in the top here, which is a circle shape,
or the shortcut key O, will allow you to do something called proportional editing.
Proportional editing will allow you to not only manipulate the
vertices that you just selected, but its surrounding neighbors as well to the
degree that you control. Okay? So now if I do GZ, you'll see that there's a gray
circle there that if I roll my mouse button, it gets bigger and smaller.
This gray circle is the area of influence.
So the move before-- So I'm going to turn off
proportional editing. And once again, if I do GZ to move these dots upward, it only
pulls up those dots, and every other dot around it doesn't get affected at all.
However, if I turn on proportional editing with O or click this button up here and
do GZ, depending on the size of my area of influence, it will bring up its
neighbors as well.
Okay? So if I make the circle smaller, the influence is smaller.
If I make the circle bigger, it influences more of the surface, the
mesh that I'm playing with.
Cool, right? I think that this should be a wow moment for some of you.
Okay, so one vertex. Now I'm going to try to manipulate this GZ one more time and
reduce the area of influence and drag this up.
And you can do it dynamically. As you pull it up, you can change what gets
manipulated.
So very cool. So proportional editing, shortcut key O. Okay?
Mesh modeling. Okay, so now let's go-- I'm going to return to Control + Z to return
all of these things back to normal.
Tab to go back into
object mode. I'm going to hide my plane, and now we're going to model up.
How many of you know the game Among Us?
Do you know this game Among Us? Any of you with children are smiling because you
know very well what I'm talking about.
Okay, you know what I'm going to bring up for the rest of you who are obviously not
very cool, I need to teach you what Among Us is. Let me show you.
It is a bean-shaped character that looks something like this. Okay?
I use this to teach my kids how to do 3D modeling on Blender.
So we're going to do an Among Us character right now.
All right. So surprisingly, I'm going to Shift + A, add a cube. You're like, "What?
It's a bean shape. Why the heck are you starting off with a cube?" The reason I
start off with a cube is because the few--
Think of modeling on Blender like you're sculpting.
You're going to start off with a block of material, and you're going to create a
rough shape of it first and then slowly refine it into its smooth,
curvaceous face that you'll end up wanting to do.
So if you look at pictures of people sculpting sculptures, the beginning shape of
it is very, very rough. And the reason we want to do that is the fewer number of
faces that are present in a Blender modeling situation, the less demand
it will be on your computer. If you immediately put 1,000 subdivisions onto this
cube and then you try to move it around, it's going to make your computer very,
very slow, and it's going to heat up and get hot.
So we're going to create this by using the least amount of shapes that we can.
However, I'm going to use a modifier here.
Because it's a bean shape, I'm going to go add modifier, generate subdivision
surface to turn it into something that generally looks like a bean. Okay?
And this is going to be my starting point.
I'm going to change the level viewport from level one to level two to give it a
little bit more subdivisions, but not too many.
And then I'm going to apply this modifier. I'm happy.
I want it to be round, so instead of leaving it non-destructive and preview, I can
click on this down arrow, click Apply.
Let me show you what happens when you don't apply it.
So from object mode, if I hit Tab to go into edit mode, it still thinks of this
object as a cube. Right? And we can actually manipulate it in this way.
For instance, if I scale it in the Z direction, I can stretch this out to be more
like the Among Us character while maintaining a cube.
And it's still, because it thinks it's a cube, it's less demanding on the computer.
Right? The Among Us character is more flat, so I'm going to scale it in the Y
direction, S-Y to scale it, to flatten it a little bit like this.
Okay? And G-Z to move it up above the work plane because he's going to have legs,
and object mode to go back. All right, so that's the beginning of my Among Us
character. But from this point, I want to be able to access all of these little
subdivisions within
the geometry I just made. So I'm going to have to apply this modifier.
So go with the down arrow, hit Apply, and now when I hit Tab, I go back in.
It's got all of the subdivisions baked into it. Okay?
So as you saw, I think, let me see. If I go back to Among Us one more time.
This character is very, very simple. It's got only a few features.
It's got a face, it's got a backpack, and it's got two legs.
So that's what we're going to do to model.
And because it's symmetrical, I don't want to have to model two arms, two legs, and
so on and so forth. What I can do is to model only half of this object.
So here I am in
edit mode with minus Y. Okay, I want to make sure minus Y is facing in this
direction, and I know here, minus Y. So this is the front of my guy.
There's a button here, which is two squares overlapping one another.
This is X-ray mode. So if I click on that, I can see the dots on my object, both in
the front and the back, and I'll show you why this is important.
If I don't have X-ray mode turned on and I look at this object directly from the
front and I do a selection like this with a left mouse click drag,
it selects all of the vertices that it can see, but all the vertices in the back
that it cannot see is not selected. Okay? I don't want that.
Right now, I want to be able to select front and back simultaneously, so I turn on
X-ray mode, so I can see both front and back.
And now when I do selection of half of the object, it selects everything from front
to back. It's a very useful tool, okay?
I'm going to delete half all of these things by hitting X for delete and choosing
to delete faces, and I'm left with a half of a bean. Okay?
And now I'm going to use another modifier.
I'm going to select A to select all, go to add modifier, generate mirror, and
it's going to create the other half for me.
And make sure that when you use the mirror modifier, that you also select clipping.
Okay? This is very important. A lot of you will forget to do this, and it creates a
mess. Make sure you select clipping when you use the mirror modifier.
Okay, so why am I doing this? Is because now when I make changes on this side, it
automatically gets reflected on the other side as well. It saves me a lot of time.
Okay, wonderful.
Let's create a face. So how do I do that?
Hit three to-- First of all, I'm going to turn off
X-ray mode just so I don't accidentally select something in the back of the object.
Hit three to do face select. I'm going to
click and select these four faces.
I can do that by holding down the shift key and just doing this.
Or a faster way to do it is to left mouse click and drag and kind of intersect
those four desirable things. And this is going to be your face, okay?
With these four faces selected, you're going to hit E on your keyboard for extrude,
and you're going to punch it out a little bit for the face.
It's going to look like that. Now I'm going to go back to the back of the object,
and I'm going to do a backpack. Okay?
So once again, selecting the ones I want,
I think. Yeah, that's good. And then do an E.
And actually, you can control it by doing E-Y to make sure it extrudes directly
backwards.
Okay, so that's my backpack.
And one thing, so far I've not done any saving whatsoever, and that's super, super
dangerous because you will have done many, many, many things, and then you will try
to do a render, and your computer will crash, and you'll lose everything.
So don't forget to save. So Control + S to save. And here we go.
Next, we're about 70% there. We're going to create some legs.
I'm going to go back to vertex select mode, select a vertex here, generally where
the legs are going to be. Hit X to delete and hit faces. Oops, sorry.
No, I need to... Sorry, let's do three.
For face select, select these four squares.
I'm going to hit X to delete and faces, and I get a hole where the legs are going
to be.
Hit two to do edge select. And here's a new feature.
I can go, and I can select one edge at a time, holding the S, the Shift key to
select all of the edges that generates the loop around this leg.
Or the shortcut key is to hit the Alt key.
I believe on a Mac, that's the Option key, I think.
You guys don't have Alt, you have Option.
If I hold down the Alt key and then select one of the edges, it automatically
selects the entire loop for you. So this is a really, really good time-saver for
you. And the guy's legs are a little bit...
It's round.
Should I do this or should I not?
Yeah. This is a little bit of
advanced technique, but I will show you anyway.
Up at the top here, you have a selection of menus, Mesh, Transform, To Sphere.
And ooh, boy, why am I getting everything?
Okay, proportional editing is still on, so it's affecting everything.
What I want to do is the legs of the Among Us character is round.
And right now, if I extrude this, it's going to create a very square leg, but I
want a round leg. So Mesh, Transform, To Sphere.
And when I move my mouse left and right, it makes that hole a little bit more
round. Okay? So now you can see it's gone from a rectangular shape to a round
shape.
Okay? And now we're going to do another extrusion straight downwards.
So E, Z, to go straight down, make it pretty long, like that, and
you'll understand why later. Now I want this selected zone, this selected edge
to be parallel to the Z plane, to the surface of my work
plane. A shortcut key for that is to scale in the Z direction, zero,
and it flattens out everything. One more time.
S, Z, zero will take a diagonal set of
points and flatten it out. Okay? Nice shortcut key.
So now it's nice and flat to the bottom here.
And you've got a hole, and if you want to fill the hole, you hit F for face, and it
fills in the hole.
The legs are a little bit too long, so I'm going to move this up with G, Z, bring
it up to like this. And now my Among Us character has now been created.
Actually, he looks too much like a bean, and I want to make this part a little bit
more straight, so I can add some extra, another loop at this level here.
And to add loops or a loop cut in Blender, you do Control + R, and you can add
another loop in this position. If you roll your mouse, you can add extra loops.
I only need one, so I'm going to do this click, and now I have an extra loop.
And with proportional editing turned on,
I'm going to move it down. G, Z. And my circle is very big.
I want to change the influence to about that much.
And now I can move it down, and it has a little bit-- I can change the shape a
little bit. Okay, like that. That to me looks a lot more...
What do you think, Tina? Is that pretty Among Us to you?
Yeah, you're good with that? Okay, back to
object mode. Now you're thinking, "Oh my God, it's so ugly. It's so blocky.
It's not interesting." So here's where the magic of modifiers comes in again.
The first thing you can do is you can just simply right mouse click and go Shade,
Smooth. And it sort of makes it a little bit better than it was before.
But it's not good. It's not good, and I'm going to undo that.
It's not good because there's not enough geometry for this thing to create smooth
surfaces. So now we're going to do subdivision surface one more time to add some
extra geometry. So Add Modifier, Generate Subdivision Surface, and
it's, see, already looking a lot better.
I'm going to make this level two to make it super smooth.
And now when I-- you can still see squares here.
If I right-- Actually, before I do that, I need to add colors.
Now with fewer things to select, I'm going to add colors to this thing.
All right, so let's go to color preview mode. Red ball. How am I doing on time?
Okay, I'm still within the hour, I think.
Okay, so we go to New. I'm going to call this material body.
And Tina, what's your favorite color?
What's your favorite Among Us character?
The red one.
Red one. Okay, so I'm going to make it red. All right.
But then, his face plate is a different color.
So we have to add a new material, and we're going to call this one face plate.
Face.
Okay, and I think it's kind of white, but I'm going to make it a little bit bluish
because that's what I want to do. Okay, a little bit bluish.
And
like that, blue-white. All right, so if you remember, we just have to get into edit
mode.
Face select, and I'm going to select these surfaces, hold down the Shift key,
select all of the other surfaces here.
And now go select a face color and assign it. And now I got a white face plate.
Okay, now with that's done, object mode, go back to subdivision surface,
generate subdivision surface, do a viewport level two.
Okay. You can still see little squares inside here.
You can right mouse click and choose Shade Smooth.
And now he's completely sexily smooth.
Okay, so another thing to personalize it, to make it a little bit more your own, we
can even go in there and do a little bit more decoration on this, right?
Once you do this on a human being, which we'll get to, I promise you that you're
going to make a human avatar today, and we'll do that in the second hour.
But let me show you how to do some
micro decorations on this thing. It's the same technique as we used to add colors
to things. So we're going to go in here.
Let's create a third color, and we're going to call this
decoration.
And I'm going to make it dark gray
for my decoration, okay? And for instance, I want to put eyes and a mouth onto my
guy. So hitting the Tab key, I need to apply my subdivision.
So I need to go back to modifier, apply my subdivisions, go back to the Tab key to
get in here. Now I can select,
face select three, face select add these two, and maybe, yeah.
And then go back to my color, assign. Now I have eyes.
Nope, I don't like the position of that. Let's go closer. How about here?
Assign. Okay, now I have eyes. Maybe let's give it a mouth, too.
Okay. And then to make it even more fun, we can go to the back here.
I'm going to use a face color because it's
easier. It's a nice color. And I'm going to put some symbol on the back.
Actually, and go back to my modifier and apply the mirror modifier as well.
Since I'm not going to change the object anymore, go back to Tab,
and I'm going to put a design here. Let's do
this.
Shift.
That was supposed to be a heart.
I'm terrible at this bit art stuff. Okay. Does that look like a heart?
It kind of looks like a heart. I'm going to call that a heart.
All right, and then go to my materials, face, assign. All right, and then Tab.
So now your guy has a face, has a heart symbol on the back, and you can decorate it
to your heart's content
Okay, I'm going to do incremental save,
and add my object.
Okay. So that's one hour gone. I did pretty good on time management.
How are we so far? Any questions that I can answer at the moment?
Thank you, Ezra, for the
validation.
Sometimes I feel like I'm talking to myself.
Okay, so with that, go ahead and take a 5-minute break or 10-minute break, and then
we'll come back, and we'll work on Make Human.
So in between, let's make it 10 minutes, and between now and then, I would actually
like, if possible, for you to open your Blender because a lot of what I'm going to
show you is a settings thing. How to install Make Human inside of Blender, so then
you can make your own thing. And this one you can follow along very, very easily,
okay? So 10 minutes, please install Blender, the latest version, and we will
resume afterwards, okay? All right, cool.
Ringo, sorry,
is it possible to ask a question?
$5. Yes, go ahead.
I have Mac, but I tried to install the latest version. It didn't allow me.
So I installed the third latest.
Okay. What version is it?
4.3.
Oh, really?
Yeah. It didn't allow.
That's surprising. Okay, let me see what's going on.
Is that a Mac problem or a Blender problem?
Let me share screen, and we can take a look at this issue together.
Are you seeing my download screen? Yes. Okay. Download Blender. Okay.
Mac OS.
You definitely-
Yeah. My Mac is Ventura
1.3, I think.
Okay.
Yeah, Ventura, and the silicone doesn't work on my iMac.
Yeah.
But is it a big problem? Yeah.
No, it should not be a problem, but I don't know. The issue is this.
Blender updates all the time, and every time it updates, some functionality of
it, which was used in a previous version, no longer works the same way in the new
version. So I just don't want to be in a situation where you're like, "How come it
doesn't work on my Blender?" So I just don't know what will and will not work, but
let's just work with what we can work with. Okay?
Okay. Thank you so much. Yes.
Let's see what we can do.
Mm-hmm.
I'm not a Mac guy at all, so I will do my best to answer Mac questions, but I'm a
coding-
Yes, and I'm so alien to coding or anything, so
That's okay.
So, yeah.
Don't worry about it. You stick with me, by the end of Fab Academy, you're never
going to ever say that again. You're going to be feeling like super.
Okay. Thank you so much. Okay. See you.
Okay. 10-minute break.
Okay.
Has it been 10 minutes? I have no idea.
Okay. Is everybody back?
Mostly? Let me see. Let me see if I can see everybody's faces.
All right. Run, run, run to your seat. It's time to get going.
Thank you, Rebecca.
Where are you from, Rebecca? I love your image.
Rebecca FL.
Where are you from?
Hi. I'm from Spain-
Spain.
But I live in Brussels. Yes.
But you live in Brussels? Okay.
Yes.
Where in Spain?
And I don't have a camera, I'm sorry.
That's okay.
I had put my laptop closed.
Where in Spain are you from?
I'm from the north, from Galicia.
Galicia. That must be somewhere near Leon, Nuria?
Yes, it's next to the Atlantic Ocean.
Okay. Okay. My daughter is going to school in Segovia right now.
Wow. Is she liking it?
She loves it a little bit too much, I think.
Oh, yeah?
I'm expecting a Spanish boyfriend to show up in Japan one of these days soon.
Let's put it that way.
Okay. Very nice. Okay, great. Let's see. What are we looking at?
A blank Google screen. MakeHuman. Let's go there.
How many of you have used MakeHuman before?
One.
Okay, so MakeHuman is an amazing
application that allows you to make avatars like this.
So, it has a... I don't know if this is internet-based or it's an app.
I'm not sure. I think it's an installed app.
But you can get in there, and you can do things like change the gender, age,
muscle, so on and so forth to get the character that you want.
So, as I promised, you're going to be able to generate your own avatar.
And then with all of those blender modeling techniques I just showed you, you can
add all kinds of different features.
For instance, if you want to add an extra arm or if you want to have a cyborg
extrusion pop out of the head, you can do that as well.
So that's why we spent that time making the perfume bottle and the Among Us
character, because I want you to understand how to manipulate things.
I just realized I didn't stop the recording while we went to the bathroom.
Okay, well, I'll make sure to cut that out.
Anyway, the wonderful thing here is that this awesome software has a
direct blender integration, which means you can do all of these wonderful MakeHuman
things directly in Blender and without using two different softwares.
And you do that by going here to MPFB.
And I think it stands for MakeHuman something for Blender. What does it stand for?
MakeHuman. Anyway, you go click on this,
MPFB.
Yeah, okay. And you can go to MPFB download.
And where you go to get it. Okay, so yeah, not a great website.
Primary Mirror is where you want to go.
So it says here, this is where you usually download MPFB2.
I guess that's the newest version. So I think, do you click somewhere here?
Where can you get this?
Maybe here? I don't know. I'm sorry.
Downloads.
CMP downloads. Where is it? Here. Okay, once I find it, I'm going to send you
the link.
Where? MPFB downloads. I'm here.
I did it in Blender. I just put it from Blender directly.
Okay. But I want to do it this way because you're going to have to download more
than just the program itself. Okay.
Yeah, let's do it in Blender, and then we'll come back here for other things.
Okay, so back to Blender.
I'm going to hide my little friend here.
Okay, so Blender
is powerful as its own software, but you can add extra functionalities to it,
add-ons that will give it additional things that it can...
Because it's an open-source software, other developers have created extra features
to it that you can choose to download and add to your thing, and you do that by
going to the Edit menu, Preferences, okay? And in Preferences, you see Add-ons.
Okay? If you go to add-ons and you go up here and type MPFB, it should
show up. If it doesn't show up, go to Get Extensions, which is above Add-ons, and
type MPFB.
All right, so you guys do that right now and tell me if you're able to find it,
because mine is already installed.
Who was it that said you installed directly in Blender?
Tina. Okay, did you do it through Extensions or Add-ons?
I got it through Get Extensions.
Extensions. Okay.
I have Blender version 2.1, I think it was.
If you're not able to find it in Extensions, it might be because you are not
allowing Blender to search the internet, and you allow that by going to System,
and here. There's a network, and it says, "Allow online access." You want to make
sure that's checked. If that's checked, then whenever you go to Extensions and
search for anything, it should be able to find it, okay?
Dear Rico, can you please show one more time?
I opened the Preferences, but
I'm not sure what I should-
Okay. So in the middle, you should see Add-ons, and right above that-
Add-ons. Mm-hmm
... you should see Get Extensions.
And in Get Extensions, there's a search menu at the very top center.
Mm-hmm.
If you type MPFB there, you should be able to find
the MakeHuman
add-on. And I think there should be an Install button next to it once it arrives.
Is anyone having trouble finding MPFB via Blender?
If you are, raise your hand or unmute and let me know. Oh, good.
Everybody's good on that. All right.
So once MPFB is installed on your computer,
in my case, make sure that the checkbox next to it is checked.
If it's like this, it's not being activated.
Make sure that it's checked so that it's activated.
Because once it's activated, you come back to the...
By the way, is everybody caught up? Everybody's caught up? Yeah. Okay.
If you hit the N key, the side menu comes up, and you'll see that MPFB 2.0 is one
of the options that shows up as a feature.
Good. All right. But before we use it, we do need to download some extra things,
and here's where we need to go back to the MakeHuman website into
the Downloads folder. We need to download some assets, right?
So the Blender MPFB as it is will allow you to generate a
human being, but you will not be able to add eyes or hair or clothing or anything
like that. So it'll be a naked, eyeball-less human being, which is pretty
terrifying, and you don't want that.
So, let's go back here and make sure we get some extra stuff to make sure we can
get hair and things like that. And that's done through asset packs here.
So you click Asset Packs. I'm going to put the link to this here
into the chat if I can find the chat. Where's my chat? Here.
Uh-oh, somebody said that you don't see my screencast.
I'm sorry, I haven't been looking at the chat at all.
Stephanie, love your character. My God, I should have done this during the break.
Is there written sources with these commands? Yes.
If you Google Blender shortcuts, there are lots and lots of these things.
I know you found it already.
Okay.
All right, so here is the asset pack.
The one that you really need is right here, MakeHuman System Asset.
Please download that. MakeHuman System Assets.
Okay, so if I click on that, it will show you all of the lovely things you get in
this asset pack. Hair, yay. Eyes, yay.
What else do we have? Eyebrows, yay. So many wonderful things.
Hats, some generic clothing.
All these things will come with this
Make Human system asset. Okay. You know what?
I can send you this link as well in the chat.
Okay. For the time being, I need you to download this into your download folder and
do not extract it. Do not unzip it, just leave it there.
And just for once you get better at this, then you might want some other things.
Like for you guys, you might want poses, for instance.
There are some generic poses here that you can download that you might want to be
able to use. So go ahead and if you want, you can download poses.
There's some extra hair here if you are dissatisfied with the generic hairstyles.
This one gives you more hairstyles, hair color.
Anyway, all these assets are available to you. Poke around and play with it.
For now, let's go back to Blender and continue.
All right. So before we do any fun things, we have to do one
more other thing is-
Sorry, a quick-
Yeah
... a quick question about downloading.
It gives me two options, mirror one or mirror two. Is both okay?
Either one is fine. Basically, it's a server in one location versus a server in
another location. Doesn't matter.
Okay.
Yeah. Good question.
Where are you from, Izzy?
I'm from England, actually.
Okay. And you're in England right now?
No, actually I'm in Amsterdam right now.
Oh, okay. You're an Englishman in Amsterdam. English person in Amsterdam.
Yes, very much.
Very good.
All right. So please,
one more time, hit N
in Blender to open up the side panel, and you should see MPFB as a tab.
Click on that tab, okay? And you'll see a bunch of different
panels in that. Click on system and resource. No, not system and resources.
Hold on, give me a second.
Oh no, it's not here. We need to go back to edit preferences
and add-ons and go to your MPFB here.
And next to MPFB, you see a right-pointing arrow.
Click on that to expand MPFB, so you can see more of it.
What's critical here is we need to create a path to...
You can't really see it, but here it says, path to MPFB user data.
This folder is where you're going to install and keep all of your assets and stuff
like that, so that MPFB for Blend will know to look there for hair and clothing and
things like that that you've downloaded. Okay? So you need to create that.
I'm not sure how to do it on a Mac. So on Windows, I would say I would go to my
Windows Explorer. I would go somewhere like Documents, right?
I would create a folder called MPFB. So I created one already called MPF...
Oops, sorry. I created one already called MPFB data. Okay?
In Windows, I would right mouse click here and copy as path to get the path
to that folder, and then I would go back to preferences, add-ons,
MPFB, path to MPFB user data, and paste the path to my
folder into that spot.
Anybody can help me to understand how to do that on Mac?
I
think you could make a right click and say copy path to a folder.
Mm. I don't remember.
Um.
I think that you have to right click that info, and then you can see the path and
then copy paste.
Sorry, one more time, Erin.
So right click on your folder and then get info, and then it says where, and you
have the path, and this I think you have to copy paste.
Okay, perfect. So, when I do it on Windows, my path comes with quotes on either
side. That you need to delete the quote marks so that it's just
my drive C, user, so on and so forth, and MPFB data as the final thing.
And when that's set in there, you need to go on the lower left-hand side of the
preferences window. There's a hamburger icon. And make sure you save preferences.
This is critical, okay?
Save preferences. And now MPFB will know that this folder's here.
Actually, I think we need to shut down Blender and come back in, for this to be
well understood. So I'm going to go ahead and do that right now.
I'm going to kill Blender and save my file and restart it again.
Maybe on a Mac that's not required because you guys are...
It's a more enlightened PC. Okay, and I'll go back to tutorial.
Oops, not this one file. Oh, it doesn't matter.
Sorry, just one question. Do you have to export the zip in the folder once it's in?
Ah, okay. So I'll show you how to do that next. Do not do any of...
You do that within Blender. So we'll do that exactly right now, okay?
Okay, so if you're back in Blender, one more time, N key to open up the side panel,
click MPFB, and now we're going to...
There's a panel called Apply Assets.
Apply Assets.
In Apply Assets, there's a category called Library Settings.
You're going to open that.
At the bottom of library settings, it says load pack from zip file.
Oh, first of all, move everything into your MPFB data folder.
If you haven't done that already, move everything into your MPFB data folder so
that it knows how to go there to look for things.
Rico, you said N key to open the... What does N key mean?
Uh-
Sorry. The letter N on your keyboard. So this side panel here disappears, okay?
But if I type the N, the letter... Oh, sorry, my screencast is not showing anymore
because I shut down. Okay, let me do that one more time.
Mm-hmm.
You see here? These are the keys that I'm touching.
So I hit N and the side panel pops open. That's what that means.
Uh-huh. When-
Okay? And amongst the tabs you have on the right-hand side, one of them should say
MPFB.
Yes. Okay. Thank you so much. Yes.
Okay. And when you select that, there's a panel called Apply Assets.
Yes. Okay.
In Apply Assets, you want to go to Library Settings.
Mm-hmm.
In the bottom of library settings, there is a load pack from zip file.
So you're going to click on that and then go to your Make Human data
folder where all of your stuff is located.
Make Human data folder
here,
and then click on that asset file that you just selected. Okay?
The one that says Make Human system assets or whatnot.
Once you've done that, all of those eyeballs and... Yes, Izzy.
Hi. I'm sorry I really cannot find it.
Ah, okay.
I can press the N and the-
Why don't you share screen?
One second will do.
Go ahead and share screen so I can take a look at what you have.
Yeah. One second.
Okay. So I'm here. I pressed the N.
Give me a second. It's still loading for me.
Oh.
Yep.
This is with N clicked.
Yep. It's not showing up because MPFB has not been selected.
You need to go to edit. Go to the edit menu.
Uh-huh.
Preferences.
One second.
Hmm.
Okay. Add-ons.
Add-ons. Mm-hmm.
MPF. Go to the search at the top and type MPFB.
Okay, you haven't... MPFB. B like boy.
Okay, you haven't installed it. That's why. Now go to get extensions.
Okay.
Ah, and then click allow online access.
Okay. And then in here, type MPFB.
B like boy,
and hit Enter.
Remote data unavailable. Remote repository. It might be your system.
Okay, can we go to System?
Okay.
And okay, Allow Online Access is on. Get Extensions. Hmm.
Okay. This is where we're going to need to install it directly from the site
itself. Can you-
I already did that. You mean about the MakeHuman? I already did this.
You downloaded the asset pack, right?
Yes. And also,
I downloaded the asset pack and also this app. The app.
You did?
The MPFB. Okay.
Right.
Can you go to the website and show me what you downloaded?
One sec. So I downloaded the asset pack.
Uh-huh.
And then I also downloaded the most recent one here.
Oh, great. Perfect. Okay, perfect.
But I have this separate-
Okay, so let's install it. Let's go to-
Like an application?
Yeah, let's go to...
Add-ons?
MPFB is the Blender version. So let's go to add-ons. Can you go to add-ons here?
Yeah.
Okay,
great. And go this down-pointing arrow.
I want you to go to down-pointing arrow over here on the right side.
Okay. Yep.
And install from disk.
Okay, perfect. MakeHuman?
Uh-
So I install from there?
Can you look in your downloads folder?
Is there a MakeHuman community?
I wonder if that's it.
That was what I downloaded as that first page, because I-
Try that. Try that one, and hit install from disk and see if it works.
Okay.
Nope. Okay.
No?
Give me a second here while I try to figure out what file you're supposed to
download.
Okay.
Windows.
Yeah, MPFB. There are two things, as I mentioned.
There's the MakeHuman app, which you run on your desktop, and there's a MakeHuman
add-on for Blender. What we want is to download the add-on,
but I'm struggling to find where that is.
Asset packs. Give me a second here. I'm sorry, it's taking a long time.
Hmm. It's telling you to do it. Okay, so
everybody else, I'm assuming, has successfully installed MakeHuman, right?
Where is my...
Oh, here. Chat. Okay.
Sorry, just one question. I installed MakeHuman, but I don't know which
assets we should
transfer, or if we should just start with Blender. I don't know.
Okay. So let me handle your question next.
Izzy, in the link-
Sure
... there's a website that you need to go to, and there's a button called Get
Add-On on that page. Why don't you go there?
Scroll down. Right side, Get Add-On, click that.
And then drag and drop into Blender?
Drag and drop into Blender.
That should work.
Oh.
It disappeared.
Try it again.
Yeah.
If you-
Drag it and drop it into the 3D viewport window.
Yeah. One sec. Ah.
There we go.
Sorry, one second.
No worries. I know. It's a nightmare trying to do this-
There's a-
... in real-time.
There we go.
Okay.
"Repository found. This extension..." Okay.
One second. It said, "Repository found was not found in a remote
repository." Yeah.
This part of the repository and compat... Check that this part... Hmm.
Not 100% sure. Let's just make sure that it didn't successfully install.
And we might have to debug this afterwards. I'm going to have to look into this.
Mm-hmm.
Okay, so go ahead and go into your preferences again.
Edit, Preferences, Add-ons, and let's see if
MPFB is already in there.
It's... Yeah. No.
Can you type MPFB at the top?
No. Huh.
Okay. Izzy, I'm going to have to come back to you later on.
I'm a little bit curious-
Yeah
... as to why this is happening. All right.
So then the other question came from who?
Sorry. It came from me.
Hi, Vida. Okay.
Hi.
The asset pack that you need to... I'm going to share screen.
All right. What are we looking at here?
Okay. So under MPFB downloads, you want to go to Asset Packs, which is
here.
And out of Asset Packs, the only one right now that you need to install is this one
here, MakeHuman System Assets.
Mm-hmm.
So, right, I'm in the assets part, and then MakeHuman-
Assets part of what? Blender?
Yeah, just click on the link that you shared.
Oh, okay.
But, so-
Why don't you share your screen? Let's do it this way, so I can at least see what
you're doing.
Okay. But I don't know how to... Wait, sorry. I'm sorry.
Hi.
Can I say something?
Yeah.
Maybe it's because, I was confused too, but that there is the Miro one and the Miro
two link you have to download from. Maybe that's the problem?
Mm.
I don't think so. The error message that Izzy got seems to indicate that it's a
version incompatibility issue.
I was thinking of Rita's problem.
Oh, Rita's problem. Okay.
Wait.
Are you able to share screen?
Yeah. Probably. Yeah. Okay. So I just go here.
This is a fundamental Fab Academy skill.
You're going to need to be really good at this.
How do I share screens? I never shared a screen before.
At the bottom toolbar, there is a share button. It's a rectangle with an up arrow.
Oh, okay. Yeah.
Yeah. If you click that, and it'll give you options of what you want to share.
Yeah.
So I suggest you share the one that says whole screen or everything or something
like that.
Okay.
It says that I'm not allowed to share. Why?
Um.
I don't know.
It says that anybody can share right now.
It says, I want to click on share, but it doesn't give me that option.
It doesn't allow me to click it.
Everybody else can share, right? Izzy, you just shared, so-
Yeah
... Vida, I don't know what's going on on your side.
Okay. But can I just... Okay, I will learn this after, but I don't want to slow
you.
Okay.
So,
just my question was, I was on the assets part, and then-
In Blender, you mean?
Yeah. I was on the add-ons.
Okay. Let me go back to my... Let me share my Blender screen,
so that
maybe you can walk me through it.
Yes. Walk me through it.
So you're here, Edit-
Yeah.
References, Add-ons, right?
And then MPFB.
Wait. Okay.
Right?
And all Is this what you're talking about? Yeah.
But where do I see MPFB?
Like... You have to install it. If you haven't installed it, it won't show up
there. Oh, okay. So I still have to install that. Okay.
Yeah.
Okay.
MakeHuman has a YouTube channel that shows you how to install all of these things.
So we'll leave you to that. Okay. And if you still struggle with it, do let me know
in Mattermost, I'll help you. But in the meantime, I'm going to move forward, okay?
Mm-hmm. Okay. All right.
So the last thing we were doing, we were doing Apply Assets, Library Settings, Load
Pack from Zip File, and you should have selected the MakeHuman System Assets zip
file to open, which should have been installed in your
MPFB data folder that you created.
With that done, we can now make somebody a human being. Okay?
So what you do to make a human being is you go, there's a panel called New Human.
You click on that, and you're going to do it from scratch.
And here you make your adjustments. All right, I'm going to make this interactive.
So Izzy, tell me, gender, neutral, male, or female?
Neutral. Neutral. Okay. Age, young, child, baby.
Wait. Old, young, child, or baby? Baby. Baby. Okay.
Muscles, minimum, average, maximum?
Maximum. Maximum muscle baby. Okay. This is going to be fun.
Weight, minimum, average, maximum?
Me again?
What? Minimum- Someone else. I'll go maximum ... maximum. I'm maximum.
This is going to be your character. Yeah.
This is your avatar right here we're creating in real time.
Height, short, average, tall?
Average. Average. Okay. Proportion, inverted V shape, average, or
V shape? Inverted V shape. Inverted V shape.
Race, universal, African, Asian, Caucasian? Universal. Universal. It's my baby.
All right. And here we have breasts, larger or smaller? Smaller.
Smaller? Okay. Breast firmness, more firm, less firm? Less firm.
I'm a little bit uncomfortable asking you these questions, but let's move forward.
Okay. So with that, that's basically everything.
And by the way, if you for whatever reason didn't like the choices you made, there
are ways to adjust this later. So with that, you simply do Create Human, and voila,
you've created a, what was it again?
Neutral baby, maximum muscle- The baby looks way too normal for me. ...
maximum weight, average height. Yeah. So this is- Looks way too normal for me.
I thought it was going to be real freaky with those settings.
And as you noticed, no eyeballs, very creepy.
But hey, we can play with this some more later, okay?
So with this, let's give it some eyeballs, and this is where the assets become very
helpful. So Apply Assets. This time, instead of Library Settings, we're going to go
to Skin first. Let's give it some skin.
Sorry, is that possible to ask a question now or not?
Yeah, sure. Go ahead.
I made a Create Human, but I still have the cube.
Oh, so you want to hide the cube? Same here. I don't see the baby.
How to do that?
Oh, wait. The Make Human created a cube instead of a baby?
I
created a human just how you showed, but I still had the cube.
So now I don't see the baby.
You want to hide the cube. You go to the upper right-hand corner, and in the
Outliner section, and find Cube, and then click on the eyeball icon, and it will
hide it.
Mm-hmm.
Up here. So, my cube is still there.
So if I click on eyeball here, I hide the cube.
Okay. Perfect. I have the baby. Yes. Thank you so much.
You have a baby inside the cube. Baby in a box.
It was.
Yeah.
I don't know why my assets are also not loading, and I thought I had everything
figured out here.
Am I getting color? Oh, it might be my thing. Oh, there we go. All right.
So I just picked the first one, middle-aged African female as the coloration, okay?
And now let's do some eyeballs. Okay.
Before you can add eyes, you need to add a rig, a posing
mechanism inside. So before we do that, we go to Rigging, and we go to Standard
Rig, and we're going to just say Add Standard Rig.
And you'll see these lines appear inside the baby, and later on, I'll show you that
you can use this to move the baby's pose around, okay?
With this rig added, now you can go back and add eyes.
The reason being, the eyes need to go somewhere, and it needs to go at the end of
this rigging stalk, okay? So you're going to go to Apply Assets,
Eye Library, and I don't know why mine is not showing up, but I'm going to do Add a
Low Poly Eye, and I click that.
And you see now he has eyeballs. Okay.
And now she, he, I'm not sure, but then now we're going to go to Eyebrows, and I'm
going to add eyebrow number one.
Okay. And the child now has eyebrows. Okay?
All right. And if you want to manipulate,
I think Izzy said that this is not radical enough for her, so we can go to the
Modeling subpanel here,
and go to
Phenotype. Under Phenotype, this is where you can start really playing with things.
So you can play with muscle and weight and all that other stuff to your heart's
content.
Okay.
All right. So I'm going to leave it like that, and I'm going to go back to Solid
View and get rid of the colors.
And here, I'm going to show you why we spent the first hour doing what we did.
Okay. N key to hide all of that stuff.
This baby is a mesh, just like the cube or the
Among Us character or the perfume bottle we just made.
So if I hit the Tab key to go into edit mode, I get my vertex points, okay?
So,
for instance, I don't know, let's
give this baby some spikes. I don't know why we would do that, but I'm going to do
it anyway. So I'm going to select that vertex, hit Shift key, this vertex, do this
vertex, and I'm going to do G, Z.
Ooh, my computer is crashing, that's why.
G, Z.
Okay, so I'm adding spikes to my baby. G, Z.
Okay?
So now baby with spikes.
So it can be manipulated, and for instance, you want a bigger nose.
You can go into edit mode, and you can try your best to select the squares.
We keep the squares that make up the nose.
This is mesh manipulation right here.
We're playing with the mesh of this character.
How am I doing on time? I still have 20 minutes.
All right, so I've got a nose, and I want to turn this guy into Pinocchio.
I'm going to do G to move, and Y the direction to move, and I got Pinocchio.
Okay.
So the Make Blender Human is a mesh that can be manipulated like any other mesh.
Okay, I'm going to undo all of that stuff for now.
And I'm going to show you how to make a bodysuit for this baby very quickly, okay?
So maybe naked baby is not so nice. So what we're going to do is, first of all, I'm
going to turn the... Go back here
And go to Edit. First of all, I'm going to hide the armature.
So in Outliner, I have something called Human Rig.
I'm going to hit the eyeball icon to get rid of all those distracting lines.
Edit Mode. So let's give this baby a shirt. Okay?
So what I'm going to do, like I did before, is to do X-ray mode, and I'm going to
select
some portion of the baby's mesh, like that. Okay?
And so I select the front and back of the mesh.
And I'm going to do Shift+D, which is to duplicate that thing that I just selected.
Oopsies.
Oops, I just did something horrible.
Okay, first I think I need to lock in the scale of this baby, Control+A, and apply
rotation and scale to the baby. Go back to here and Shift+D to
duplicate. Why is it doing crazy things?
Sorry, I'm trying to figure out what is messed up here with my baby.
Apply?
I'm going to apply all these things now.
Apply the armature? No, hide out first. Hmm.
Let's duplicate the whole baby first.
Two babies. Turn off X-ray mode. Okay, I'm going to play with this.
I think... Oh, there. This baby and hit the Tab key.
Front view,
X-ray. Select a portion of his body.
Duplicate, Shift+D to duplicate. Oh, it's doing this weird thing.
Hmm.
Okay. Blender's doing something very, very strange, I understand.
But anyway, I'm going to figure out what's going on here and come back to you
later. But the point here is that I'm selecting the area of the body that is
basically what would be a shirt. And I'm going to... Ah, sorry, Erin. Go ahead.
Yeah, I have a question. When I try to select things, I'm still in the eyebrows, so
I can only select
something which is related to the eyebrows.
I don't know how to unselect to go back to my-
Oh, okay.
So I guess the eyebrow for you is a different object than the body of the baby.
So all you have to do is select the body of the baby.
Yes.
Or you-
I don't know.
Yeah. I don't know. On the left where it says User Perspective, for me, it says
Human Eyebrow, and I don't know how to...
If I try to select the-
Yeah. I'm going to...
14 minutes to go. You share screen. Let's see what you're doing.
Can you see my screen?
I can see your screen, yes.
Yeah, so if I try to select, it just stays on-
Ah, because you're in edit mode after having selected the eyebrow as a thing.
So go back, Tab to go back to Object mode.
Okay. Yep.
And now select the body, not the eyebrow.
Yeah, now it's good.
No, not the armature, the body, the mesh that is the body. Okay.
Yeah.
Now hit Tab again.
And now you can select the body.
Perfect. Thank you.
Okay. So the key here is, thank you for doing this, but the key here is whatever
object you select before you hit the Tab key to go into Edit mode will be the thing
that gets edited in Edit mode. And everything else is going to be non-editable and
non-selectable. Okay?
Yep. Thanks.
Yeah. You're welcome.
You know what? I'm going to leave the manipulation and the shirt making to another
session anyway. So anybody else want to share?
Tina, can you show me your creature, human?
Well, I-
Virtual you.
Thank you so much, so let's see.
I just started, but I think I had...
Because you mentioned something about you have to save, right?
When you put in the asset pack?
Or next time I'll go in, it will be a... Oh.
No, no, no, you're good. You're good.
I'm good?
The only thing that you needed to save was preferences.
So if you go, do me a favor, go to Edit, Preferences.
Yeah.
And Make Human. Okay. And you don't have a path right now where it says Path to
MPFB User Data. Middle right side. Yeah, keep going down, down, down, down.
You don't have a folder defined there.
Yeah.
You need to put a path to a folder there.
Okay? After you've put the... What's that?
Path here? Path to-
Yeah.
Okay, yeah.
To a folder where you collect all your assets and everything else.
You need this to be here, or else everything will disappear after.
Yeah.
And then once you've set your path, on the lower left-hand corner, there are the
hamburger three-stripe icon, lower left-hand corner. Lower left-hand corner.
Keep going down. Yeah, click on that, and then you can save your preferences.
Okay, super.
That must be done after you've defined your user data folder.
Yes. I got lost in that when you said that earlier.
No worries. This is-
Yeah. Sure
... precisely why we're having this session.
Mm-hmm.
Okay, good. So you've successfully generated a human.
Julia, you've been very quiet. How are you doing with your human?
I think okay. I can share my screen, if you want to.
Yeah.
Looks like this right now.
Whoa, look at that. What are all the balls? Is that you?
I don't know. I'm sorry, it's in German.
So I went into Edit mode, and
I don't know why they're-
Ah, I think you selected the armature. So this is armature manipulation.
Right.
So go ahead and hit Tab to go back out.
Yes.
Or go back to Object mode, whatever that is in German.
Yeah.
Object mode. Exactly. Select the skin, not the internal bones.
But select the skin of your character.
Where?
Oh,
no, go ahead. You were doing it right. Select.
Yeah. Select that.
There we go. So that's your skin.
Yeah.
Now hit Tab to go into Edit mode.
Okay.
And now you're able to manipulate...
Do me a favor.
Right now, click outside the body. Click.
Yeah.
Okay. Using a drag select, I want you to select this
portion of the hand. Drag select this portion of the hand on the left side there.
Cool. All right. Now I want you to type G into your keyboard.
Yes.
Okay. And then move your arm around.
Now you can reposition, lengthen, do all kinds of stuff.
So the point here is to not think of your human creation as a figure, but think of
it as a mesh that you can play with all day long. Okay?
Okay.
So now click that like that, and...
Actually, undo. Control+Z to undo.
Yeah. Of course.
Let's make sure you can... You can see that. I want to select everything.
You missed a few dots in the back. So do a selection one more time.
Okay. Let's rotate around your figure to make sure everything was selected.
Okay, that looks good. Now let's do a G, lengthen that arm for me. Or let's do...
Yeah. Oh, that's the bones. That's fine. Okay. Lengthen the arm and click there.
Okay, good. And then hit Tab to go back to Object mode.
Okay. And then, yeah, so now your person has ridiculously long arms. Okay?
Okay.
Very good.
But the bones will stay normal.
The bones will stay normal for now.
Okay.
Yes. Okay, so if you Control+Z, you can undo the ridiculous thing that we just did
to get back to normal.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Erin, yes, question.
No, sorry, that was still from before.
Ah, okay.
All right. I think I'm going to... Actually, let me just show you one more thing
before-
I have a question.
Yeah. Yes, go ahead.
Yeah. Melanie speaking. I don't see the modifier in properties
tab.
Is it normal?
Modifier properties tab. Okay, can you please share your screen?
So I have two screens, so I do my best.
Okay.
Here.
I don't see the modifier tool.
Ah. Your screen is... Well, I don't, I might seem a little...
Oh, because, okay, that's very good. This is a great question.
The modifier
tool, it's contextual. So right now, uh-uh, what just happened?
So currently, I think your bones are selected, so that's why you see a green bone
and an armature character because it thinks you want to do settings for your
armature. So go ahead and click on your human person, like a skin like I said
before.
This is my screen.
Select the skin
right there.
Can you see my mark there? Yeah. Human, click on the word human in your outliner.
I'm on the human. Human?
Not human rig, but human below that.
Sorry, I have a small screen and a big screen, so.
Whoa, funky.
Hello, hello, hello.
Okay. So I don't see really well.
Not this screen. We're seeing ourselves a billion times. Hold on.
I was going to do a dance.
Okay, show me. I stop sharing.
Okay, fine. I will share my screen.
So I go to the
list-
No, no. Hold on. Hold on. Just give me a second, please. Give me a second.
I'm going to show you so that you don't have to guess.
Thank you.
All right. Let me share screen.
Okay, we're back on the baby, and I'm going to make sure my human rig is able to be
seen. Okay, and if I select the rig, okay, so if I select the rig, you see that
my properties menu looks exactly like yours, right?
Yes. Yes.
Okay.
Underneath human rig, there's a category called human with a yellow triangle.
If you click on that, then the properties menu changes to be contextual to that
object, and now you have modifier.
Okay.
Okay? So that's good. Let's play with that.
So if I have modifier, okay, let's do something really fun. Now generate.
What should we do? Let's do corkscrew.
Okay, this is going to do horrible things to my baby.
Okay, so here's where the power of modifiers.
I've now corkscrewed my baby into something like an artistic
sculpture,
or I don't know if this is art anymore.
Okay, so I've got this weird... I've done horrible things to the baby now. Okay?
And it is non-destructive. Like I said, if I click
X to just delete that modifier, he goes back to being a normal baby.
But modifiers are fun. So you can go in here and what else can we do? Triangulate.
Oh, okay, decimate. So, Anastasi had shown like a low-poly version
of figures by some artist, I can't remember the guy's name.
You could go generate, decimate, and then the ratio right now is one.
So if I take this really low, you see the baby becomes like a geometric shape.
Okay? So you can play with that. So now you got alien baby,
geometric alien baby.
Okay.
I have another question.
Yeah.
If I want just to keep the head
and to make the neck flat.
Just keep the head. Okay. All right.
So with the skin of the baby selected, I hit Tab to go to
edit mode. I'm going to select everything underneath the head like this.
Make sure it's all selected. Oh, I didn't have X-ray vision on, so that's why it
did that horrible thing. So turning on X-ray, I'm going to select everything below
the neck. I'm going to hit X to delete and faces. Oops.
It won't do it. Why? This is doing very crazy things for me.
Is this a new version of Blender Pro? Okay.
The problem right now that I think is going on, and I need to figure out the answer
to this, is that right now this MakeHuman mesh is not a true
mesh.
Okay, let me see. Let me try something.
Yeah, you should have been able to just delete a part of it, but it's not working.
And I think I need to Control D,
make a second copy, and I think let's try converting this to mesh.
Convert to mesh.
Okay. Okay. So now this is no longer a MakeHuman object, but a pure mesh, I hope.
Tab and delete
faces. Yes. Now I can manipulate it. Okay.
So what I just did there,
one more time. First, I made a copy of the baby,
the skin here by doing Shift D.
The second thing I did was do right mouse click and choose convert to mesh.
What was I trying to do earlier? Mesh manipulation.
So now if I go to tab, I'm able to... I wanted to make a shirt.
That's what I was trying to do earlier. So let's make a bodysuit for this baby.
That should work now. I'm going to do something like this.
Okay, I'm going to do Shift D to duplicate,
and I'm going to scale it slightly a little bit bigger like this.
Oops. Before deselecting it, I'm going to hit P
to separate it, and I'm going to separate it by loose parts.
But it's very advanced that we're doing here.
Turning off the
zoom and going back. Okay, so now I actually have two objects.
I have the baby
and a shirt of the baby that you can turn into clothing. Okay?
So with this, for instance, I can give it a different color.
Kill this, make this a black scuba diving suit,
and scale it up a little bit.
Okay, so I have a skin-tight suit now, a rubber suit.
G,
X. I can put it on top of the baby.
G, Y. G, Z.
Okay, it's still too close. I'm going to scale it up a little bit more to make it a
little bit bigger. Or another thing we can do is add a modifier to give it some
thickness. So go to modifier, add modifier, generate,
solidify, and by manipulating thickness, I can give this shirt
thickness.
And I have a bodysuit. I don't know. Did you see the movie Dune?
This looks like
Baron Harkonnen and his suit.
Okay. Anyway, it's 8:00 for me. Whatever it is time for you. It's been two hours.
How was that? Hopefully, it wasn't too bad.
Thank you so much.
Okay. If you are lost, confused, have questions beyond today, please drop them in
the Blender channel of Mattermost and I'll do my best to answer them.
If I remember correctly, there was an issue with downloading
Blender for Mac. There was an issue with installing the MPFB add-on
at all, with somebody due to some sort of version incompatibility.
What was the third issue? There was a third one that I couldn't remember.
But anyway, please kindly, if you cannot move forward with MakeHuman for Blender,
drop me the questions in Blender, the Blender channel, and I'll try to answer.
Okay.
That was a lot. We did a lot two hours in, but hopefully, you kind of understand
the power of the Blender software, and I can't wait to see what kinds of cool
things you make. All right?
Thank you very much.
You're welcome. All right. Bye bye. Good night.
Bye. Thank you.
Ciao.
Bye. Thank you very much.
Bye. Thanks.
Yeah.